E-mail: erik.exists@gmail.com

Webpage: http://robotpuggle.com

ABOUT ME

I'm a scientist with machine learning expertise. I've worked in both industry and academia. I'm currently work on curiosity and causality for use in artificial intelligence, and as mathematical ideas. I'm also very interested in unconventional kinds of computation in biology.

Pastuer Labs - New York, NY

Senior Research Scientist

2022 - Present

I am a technical lead building systems for automated causal reasoning on complex, multi-part, problems in physical science.

RECENT EXPERIENCE

${\bf Carnegie\ Mellon\ University}\ \hbox{-}\ {\bf Pittsburgh},\ {\bf PA}$

Research Fellow (Research Scientist)

2018 - 2022

I developed a mathematical accounts of exploration, play, and curiosity for use in reinforcement learning applications (Github) and multi-agent systems (Github).

Kernel, LLC - Los Angeles, CA

Research Scientist

2017 - 2018

I was the technical lead building a system for complex spatio-temporal field shaping in deep brain stimulation. This project blended biophysical modeling with deep neural networks and led to 400,000 fold speed up – a key requirement for real-time use.

U.C. San Diego - San Diego, CA

Postdoctoral Fellow

2014 - 2017

I conducted theoretical research on the coding properties of neural oscillations. I verified theoretical predictions using biophysical modeling, and experimental data. I also co-lead development of a python tool to analyze electrophysiological data which has found widespread use in the neuroscience community.

EDUCATION

Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO

Ph.D, Psychology

2012

California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo, CA

B.S., Chemistry and Biochemistry; Minor, Philosophy

May 2004

Programming

Python

Core ML - Linear methods to deep neural nets - {pytorch, ray, sklearn}

Expert

 \mathbf{R}

Core DS - Visualization, analysis, and statistical testing - {tidyverse}

Expert

PROJECTS

The Exploration Book (Github)

Authoring a book on exploration in biology, ranging from random search, to reinforcement learning, to curiosity, imagination, and reasoning. I developed a python package (Github) to make it easy to explore exploration.

Press & Public

Brain's 'Background Noise' May Hold Clues to Persistent Mysteries, Quanta Magazine, 2021.

Talks

Build Your Own Brainwaves, *Nerd Nite*, Los Angeles, Feb 2018. Conflicted Data Science, *Open San Diego*, San Diego, Feb, 2016. In Theory You're Paying Attention, *Ignite*, San Diego, Nov 2016.

Select

PUBLICATIONS

Donoghue T*, Haller M*, **Peterson EJ***, et al, Parameterizing Neural Power Spectra into Periodic and Aperiodic Components, *Nature Neuroscience* 23 1655-1665 (2020). [*]: Co-first.

Peterson EJ & Verstynen T, Curiosity eliminates the exploration-exploitation dilemma, bioRxiv 671362v8 (2020).